when I first started the piano I like a
lot of other people started selft talk
and if I was to start again today there
is a lot of things that I would do very
very differently so in this video I want
to tell you how you can start learning
the piano self tour including what you
need how to set goals what you should
learn and why I'm going to talk about
some common problems that a lot of
people run into how to avoid them and
how to fix them I'll give you some good
video book and course recommendations to
best fit what you want to learn and I'm
also going to talk about how to keep
going and to get better over the long
term there are definitely some
advantages to learning self-taught such
as let's be honest you can play what you
want and obviously it's a lot cheaper to
learn without a teacher however there
are also some disadvantages to learning
selftaught and that is that you don't
know what you need to learn and you can
also run into problems that are going to
affect your playing long term such as if
you don't understand something that you
need to know or if you've skipped a
certain element of practice like sight
reading but hopefully in this video I'm
going to alleviate some of those
disadvantages of playing selft talk so
let's start with what you actually need
to get started firstly you're going to
need something to play on and if you
don't have something to play on already
then the best thing to get is a digital
piano or an acoustic piano that has 88
keys weighted keys and that has a
sustained pedal if you have an
instrument that has those things then
it's going to last you a pretty long
time the other thing that you're going
to need is an idea about what you
actually want to achieve by playing the
piano that can be as simple as you want
to be able to pick up a piece of music
and play songs that you like it could be
that you want to get to grade8 piano
could be that you're a music producer
and you want to get really good at music
theory and use the piano to do that
there are lots of reasons why you might
want to learn the piano because if you
are someone for example that wants to be
able to work songs out by ear then it's
going to be pretty pointless sitting
down and reading a bark Prelude so
that's what you need let's talk about
how you're actually going to get there
so the way that I stay committed to
learning the piano without losing
motivation was to set long-term goals
short-term goals and very short-term
goals now to me long-term goals are
something that should take around 6
months to a year to complete for example
taking a graded piano exam or learning a
Beethoven Sonata longer term goals tend
to be outcome related so they're goals
where you want to get something out of
it at the end however long-term goals on
their own they're very difficult to stay
motivated which is why you should have
short-term goals and very short-term
goals these should both be based on
input rather than outcome and by that
your short-term and very short-term
goals should be based on what you
actually do rather than what you're
actually going to get out of it for
example a shortterm input goal might be
this week I'm going to practice four
times for 30 minutes and that is a goal
that is entirely dependent on whether
you do it or don't do it and then there
are very short-term goals and that is
things that you're going to do today now
once again this should be input related
rather than outcome related so it needs
to be something that you can do without
the guarantee of an outcome but your
very short-term goals should always be
in service of your short-term goals and
your short-term goals should always be
in service of your long-term goals and
here's an example for you so I might
have a long-term goal of achieving grade
one on the piano and in order to be able
to do that in 6 months time this week
I'm going to practice 6 days a week for
30 minutes and in my practice today that
is 30 minutes long I'm going to practice
two of the scales I'm going to practice
the first four bars of a piece and I
might also do four sight reading
exercises and then the key to this is
once you've actually achieved your
long-term goal then you need to set
another achievable long-term goals
straight away if you have constant
long-term back-to-back goals then it
just becomes habit and on a day-to-day
basis it's just something that you do
rather than thinking today I can't be
bothered but what do you actually need
to learn when you're first starting to
teach yourself the piano well that
largely depends on what you actually
want to get out of learning the piano
but there are five main categories of
things that you can learn the first is
sheet music reading there's scales
chords music theory and oral skills
which is just listening now I would
suggest for anyone that's teaching
themselves the piano especially at the
basic beginner level to try and start
learning a little bit of all of these
because they are all all very very
important so let's talk about what's
involved in each of these five
categories and why you actually might
want to learn them so firstly sheet
music reading you can very easily see
visually on a piece of music exactly
what's happening and composers can be
really specific when writing sheet music
as to how they want you to play it if
you just play by ear for example then
you are playing everything how you want
to play it which is not a bad thing but
learning how other people write music
and seeing what is possible in music can
expand how you interpret something
played by ear because the more music
you've read the more tools you've got
and then there's scales scales are what
music is made from on a piano there are
12 different unique keys and major and
minor scales which are the most common
types of scales narrow those 12 notes
down to just seven so if you are reading
a piece of music or you're listening to
a piece of music and you know what scale
that piece of music is using it becomes
a lot easier to work out what the note
should be and when you practice scales
on the piano what you're really doing is
giving yourself an opportunity to get
really dextrous but you're also making
that set of notes automatic in your
hands so if you know the scale of G
major really well and you come across a
piece that's in the key of G major then
your hand is going to automatically know
which notes you're going to be playing
on the keys then there's chords there
are certain patterns of chords that are
really important to learn such as Triads
or seventh chords these types of chords
are really common and come up time and
time again so if you learn the standard
patterns of chords that you're going to
see then when you see them or hear them
in a piece of music your hand is
automatically going to know where to go
and a lot of learning the piano is about
patterns and pattern recognition and
that's why people at first start
learning an instrument find it so
difficult to site read music because
what they're trying to do is read every
single individual note on the page
whereas someone who is more experienced
in music will look at a piece of music
and just see it as a set of patterns
that are happening that they've seen
before in other pieces then there's
music theory if you understand how music
works then it's very easy to write your
own music to write transcriptions or
interpretations of other people's music
if you're a singer then you can change
the key of a piece of music so that it
fits better in your vocal range so
learning music theory is very very
helpful and it's kind of interesting and
then there's oral skills and oral skills
just mean listening skills so learning
to hear different notes and how they
relate to each other and learning how
different types of chord sound if you
listen to a piece of music and you
really like that piece of
music there's no music playing and you
want to understand why you really like
that piece of music so you can recreate
it or write something similar or if you
want to be able to work something out on
the piano by ear then you're going to
want to learn how different intervals
sound and intervals just means the
distance between notes learning to use
your ears is really beneficial
especially if you want to improvise if
you want to play with other people if
you want to work stuff out by ear it has
lots of benefits so that's what to learn
and why let's talk about some common
problems that people often face when
learning by themselves the first and
probably the biggest is tension and
tension is a massive problem because
your hands aren't necessar neily going
to do what you want them to do and it
can be very tempting to force them by
tensing your hands so the first thing
you can do about this is first of all
notice if you are tense or not if your
hands start to wake or you're finding
that your hand is becoming rigid then
know that you can and need to do
something about it if your hands are
generally tense then what I would
recommend doing is using scales to
practice trying to shake your hand out
every note like
this by wobbling your hand like that it
means that your hand can't be tense
you're finding that you're just tense
when playing certain parts of pieces
then stop on the notes where you're
finding that your hand is tensing and do
the same thing so wobble your hand about
the second common problem that people
have is sitting too high or too low at
the piano now I'm probably not helping
the case here cuz I always have the
piano too high for videos and that's
just so you can see my wonderful face
and the keys at the same time however
the best way to think about why you
should sit and where the piano should be
positioned is that your arms should be
just over a right angle or 90° so if I
was trying to to sit at the correct
height for this piano I'd be sitting
kind of
there you want it to be so that your
hands can sit comfortably and you're not
having to do any weird movements to be
able to reach the keys another common
problem is people using weird fingers
and doing things like
this or putting their hand upside down
once again if you learn scales and this
does combat most of this problem because
you learn the correct fingers to use in
certain circumstances but generally if
you're playing a piece of music and
you've run out of fingers then you need
to change the fingers you used earlier
on rather than just trying to get
through the piece and playing really
random fingers and jumping around my
best advice is to just plan the fingers
that you're going to use another common
problem is people looking at their hands
rather than looking at the music looking
at your hands isn't inherently a problem
in itself the problem is if you are
trying to learn to read music then not
looking at the music is not going to
help you learn to read music it also
means that if you're reading off a piece
of music then you're missing most of the
detail that's in the music if you start
start to look at your hands as soon as
you start to memorize it so once you
played a piece of music a fair few times
and you are starting to memorize it
which will happen try and consciously
follow the music with your eyes rather
than looking at your hands another
common problem is covering mistakes
using the sustain pedal if I play a
scale and it sounds like this with the
[Music]
pedal all of those notes sound the same
but if I play the same scale like
this you can hear a very clear gap
between the third and fourth note and
that Gap was covered by the pedal which
means although my hand is not doing the
thing that I wanted to do the pedal is
covering it up so I don't know that
mistakes there so to combat this try and
play pieces with and without the pedal
and if there are mistakes without the
pedal then fix them rather than just
covering it with the pedal another
common problem is trying to learn really
quickly and forcing it a lot of people
when they first start learning think
that they should be learning more
quickly and that they're learning too
slow so they try and force it by
learning really difficult pieces or
trying to run before they can walk and
although it's okay to do difficult
pieces sometimes you've really got to be
careful that you don't try and skip a
load of things in order to get there
quicker because it will be obvious in
your playing and the last common mistake
that I see people make is that they use
stickers on their piano my blanket
recommendation would be to not use
stickers on the piano because instead of
learning what the keys actually are
you're just learning to read the letter
on the key it also means that if you're
trying to read music you're associating
the dot with the letter rather than the
dot with the key okay let's talk about
the best resources for learning the
piano as a self-taught beginner now
firstly there is a video on YouTube by a
YouTube channel called piano from
scratch which is essentially a first
lesson on how to start playing the piano
and I actually think it's a very good
video for those that have never played
before and want to know where the keys
are on the piano and that kind of thing
it does a very good job of explaining
another good video on YouTube is a video
by a channel called musicians inspired
and it's about the landmark system The
Landmark system I think is the best
method for learning how to read sheet
music and and where all the notes are on
the page and the video by musicians
inspired is very good at explaining it
and then to plug my own videos I have
done a video that is a complete guide to
using the piano pedals that is an older
video that I've made so I do sound a
little bit personality however I covered
the same topic and a lot of other topics
that might be interesting in my video
that is the top 10 most asked piano
questions and if you want to learn how
to play by ear I've also done several
videos on how you can go about starting
to learn to play by ear then there are a
couple of books that I would recommend
first of all it's the book it's never
too late to play piano by Pam Wedgewood
this is the go-to book that I use when
I'm teaching adult beginners how to
start learning the piano I think it's
very good at explaining and it's not as
slow in progressing as a children's book
might be a good book for children that
are learning is the complete me and my
piano book there are lots and lots of
beginner piano learning books out there
and all of them are equally as good
you've just got to find something that
best fits how you learn for site reading
I would recommend my site reading book
once you start learning how to read
music and you're starting to understand
the notes site reading is kind of a
different skill site reading is your
ability to read a piece of music
immediately rather than spend some time
learning it and perfecting the piece so
my site reading book which you can
download on my website is a series of
hundreds of exercises that get
progressively harder the problem that I
found with a lot of sight read material
out there is that there just isn't
enough of it if you buy a graded site
reading book for example there usually
are about 55 exercises and by the time
you've got to the end of those exercises
you're probably not that much better
than when you started but I designed the
book to get progressively harder and
because there are over 400 exercises you
can just constantly be saturating
yourself with note reading and then for
music theory I would recommend either
the discovering Music Theory series of
books or the music theory and practice
series of books by abrsm both of these
books are following the graded system so
grade one to eight and if you are an
absolute beginner get the grade one book
work your way through it and then when
you feel comfortable with that then you
can get the the grade two book and so on
it's very methodical with how you work
through the music theory and start
understanding some really complex topics
and then for courses there is a series
of Music Theory courses on udemy by
someone called Victoria Williams who
goes through some of the grades of Music
Theory and she's very good at explaining
and getting you to work through how the
music theory works and I am currently
working on a playing music by air course
myself so when that's available I will
recommend that so let's talk about how
to keep going and continuing to get
better over a long period of time
whenever starting any new skill a lot of
people get very excited to start with
and then want to practice six hours a
day but then burn out and don't want to
practice the instrument anymore I think
a lot of that problem will be solved by
setting some long-term and shortterm
goals to hold yourself accountable but
some other things that you can do are
things like recording your progress if
you record yourself playing a piece
every month or every week or something
like that then you can really start to
see your progress if you really wanted
to you could could even start a YouTube
channel documenting your progress and
then do a one year's piano progress
video and then you might find yourself
being reacted to by me other things that
you can do are things like quantifying
success and measuring it for example if
you did a 60-day challenge where you
were to try and practice 30 minutes
every day for 60 days straight by the
end of the 60 days you will know whether
you've succeeded or not and that's
something that you can quantifiably
measure and finally you can get some
feedback from peers or from musicians
there are lots and lots of Facebook
group groups with other beginners in
that are trying to learn and they're
always giving each other feedback or you
can ask musicians for their feedback you
can always ask any questions that you
have in the comments and I'll answer
them or you can book in through my
website and I will happily tell you how
to improve and I know a lot of other
musicians will do that too but if you
want to see me react to someone's one
year of piano progress then check out
this video and I will see you there